<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
       "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="faq">
<articleinfo>
	<title>Frequently Asked Questions About ResidualVM</title>
	<titleabbrev>ResidualVM FAQ</titleabbrev>
</articleinfo>

<!-- Possible values for defaultlabel: qanda, number, none -->
<qandaset defaultlabel='number'>

<qandadiv><title>Introduction</title>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>Why is it called ResidualVM - what does this name mean?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		The <ulink url="https://www.scummvm.org">ScummVM</ulink> program can run
		LucasArts 2D SCUMM adventures (among others).
		ResidualVM is named such as it aims to do the same for the residual (remaining)
		games. It is also a word pun, as the engine used in these LUA-based adventure
		games is called GrimE (as opposed to SCUMM). Grime is a type of residue.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>What is GrimE ?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		GrimE (Grim Engine) is an adventure game engine, created by Bret Mogilefsky
		at LucasArts using scripting language Lua. It was first used for Grim Fandango.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>Is ResidualVM free?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		ResidualVM is released under the <ulink
		url="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-2.0.html">GPL (General Public
		License)</ulink>, so it's more than free. ResidualVM source code is freely
		available and you can do whatever you want with it. If you make
		modifications to it and redistribute your work you MUST make the source
		available. However, the ResidualVM team would be pleased if you choose to
		send them your modifications, so they can be merged into the main tree.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>On what platform does ResidualVM run?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		ResidualVM should be able to be compiled on any SDL platform, with modifications.
		</simpara>
		<simpara>
		Currently tested platforms include Windows (Windows 2000/XP/Vista/7/8/10), Linux,
		macOS, AmigaOS 4.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

</qandadiv>


<qandadiv><title>Supported games</title>

	<qandaentry>
		<question id="question.supported-games"><simpara id="question.supported-games.text">What games does ResidualVM support?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		We have a <ulink
		url="https://www.residualvm.org/compatibility.php">compatibility
		list</ulink> on our website that contains an up-to-date list of which
		games work, and how well they work.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

</qandadiv>


<qandadiv><title>Running games</title>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>How do I install games to run in ResidualVM?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		For most games you do not need to run the installer. Simply copy
		<ulink url="https://wiki.residualvm.org/index.php?title=Datafiles">the files listed here</ulink>
		from your CD to your hard drive.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

</qandadiv>


<qandadiv><title>Troubleshooting</title>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>My game crashes at some point.</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		Check the <ulink url="https://www.residualvm.org/compatibility.php">Compatibility List</ulink> to see if your game has any known issues.
		If you can reproduce this crash more than once, please report issue.
		See "<xref linkend="question.report-bugs" endterm="question.report-bugs.text"/>".
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>ResidualVM crashes, but the console window disappears too quickly to see the error message.</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		On Windows, to make it visible, you should run ResidualVM from the command line. To open a
		command prompt, open the Start Menu and select the 'Run' option. Under
		Windows 2000/XP/Vista/7/8/10, type 'cmd.exe' (no quotes) in the dialog box that
		shows up. If necessary, change to the proper drive first by typing 'D:' (where 'D' is
		the drive ResidualVM is located). Change to ResidualVM's directory by typing
		'cd \your\path\to\residualvm' (substituting the appropriate path) and then
		type 'residualvm'.
		</simpara>
		<simpara>
		On macOS, you can find the error messages by starting Console.app
		(in Utilities within the Applications folder). If you prefer, you can
		also run ResidualVM from the terminal. To do this, start Terminal.app
		(also in the Utilities folder), then drag&amp;drop the ResidualVM.app
		application onto the Terminal window, remove the space at the end of
		the line and add 'Contents/MacOS/residualvm' (without the quotes). The
		line should look like this: '/Path/to/ResidualVM.app/Contents/MacOS/residualvm'.
		Then press return to start ResidualVM.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

        <qandaentry><question id="question.report-bugs"><simpara id="question.report-bugs.text">Reporting Issues.</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		To report an issue, please create a GitHub account and follow the
		<ulink url="https://github.com/residualvm/residualvm/issues">Issue Reports</ulink>
		link from our homepage. Please make sure the issue is reproducible, and
		still exists in the latest daily build/current Git version.
		In your issue report please provide the following information:

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><simpara>Issue details, including instructions on reproducing it</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>Language of game (English, German, ...)</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>Platform and Compiler (Win32, Linux, macOS, ...)</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>Preferably also a link to a save from just before the issue happened</simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		For further details regarding Issue Reports, please see our <ulink url="https://wiki.residualvm.org/index.php?title=Reporting_Bugs">Wiki</ulink>
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>
																																																	
	<qandaentry><question><simpara>I get "Failed to save game state to file: xxx"</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		Check savepath in Options-&gt;Paths-&gt;Save Path. That should point to writable directory.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>ResidualVM starts, but all I get is a transparent window!</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		This problem has been reported to happen under Windows in some cases. Check
		that you have the latest drivers for your graphics card. If that does not
		help, try setting the <envar>SDL_VIDEODRIVER</envar> environment variable to
		"windib" and try again.
		</simpara>
		<simpara>
		Apparently other applications have had the same problem, because the release
		notes for SDL 1.2.10 (May 17, 2006) contained the following note:
		</simpara>
		<blockquote>
		<simpara>
		The "windib" video driver is the default now, to prevent problems with
		certain laptops, 64-bit Windows, and Windows Vista/7/8/10. The DirectX driver
		is still available, and can be selected by setting the environment
		variable <envar>SDL_VIDEODRIVER</envar> to "directx".
		</simpara>
		</blockquote>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>
		
	<qandaentry><question><simpara>ResidualVM runs, but sound is stuttering and/or garbled!</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		This problem has been reported to happen under Windows in some cases. Check
		that you have the latest drivers for your sound card. If that does not help,
		try setting the <envar>SDL_AUDIODRIVER</envar> environment variable to "waveout"
		and try again.
		</simpara>
		Note using the "waveout" SDL audio driver causes an increased delay in sound,
		especially under Windows Vista and later versions.
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>ResidualVM runs in fullscreen mode, but graphics is stretched!</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		It's know issue. it will be fixed in future versions of ResidualVM.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>How do I set an environment variable?</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		That depends on what operating system and/or command shell you are using.
		Under Windows, you could try creating a file called
		<command>residualvm.bat</command> in the same folder as
		<command>residualvm.exe</command>. Open this file in your favorite text
		editor and put something like this in it:
		</simpara>
		<blockquote>
		<programlisting><![CDATA[@echo off
set SDL_VIDEODRIVER=windib
set SDL_AUDIODRIVER=waveout
residualvm.exe %1 %2 %3 %4 %5 %6 %7 %8 %9]]></programlisting>
		</blockquote>
		<simpara>
		You should now be able to run ResidualVM by double-clicking on this batch file,
		instead of the ResidualVM executable.
		</simpara>
		<simpara>
		On more recent versions of Windows, you can also set an environment variable
		permanently, and for all applications, through the control panel.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

	<qandaentry><question><simpara>ResidualVM starts somewhere in the middle of my two Xinerama monitors in fullscreen mode. Help!</simpara></question>
	<answer>
		<simpara>
		In fact, this is SDL problem. SDL does by default has xinerama support
		enabled. Set the <envar>SDL_VIDEO_FULLSCREEN_HEAD</envar>
		environment variable to "1" to start ResidualVM (and other SDL applications) in
		fullscreen on only one monitor. If this does not work make sure your SDL
		library does have Xinerama support compiled in.
		</simpara>
	</answer>
	</qandaentry>

</qandadiv>

</qandaset>

</article>
